前情提要
偷一块面包就要坐19年牢
19 years for a loaf of bread.
我猜你出狱后不到一年就会再进来
My guess, you'll be back in here before another year's gone by.
到那时候  你就要把牢底坐穿了
And next time it'll be for life.
你永远赢不了的
You can never win.
你承诺会对我好吗  菲力克斯
Do you promise you'll be good to me, Felix?
我用生命承诺
On my life.
三匹奔腾的骏马
Three galloping horses
正载着我们回到妈妈爸爸身边
will be carrying us home to our mamas and papas.
我们要走了  我们已经走了
We are leaving. We have left.
珂赛特  现在我们该怎么办
Oh, Cosette, whatever are we going to do now?
这儿好东西真不少
Rich pickings here.
你救了我的命  你是谁
You saved my life. Who are you?
德纳迪埃  先生
Thenardier, sir.
冉·阿让  我的兄弟
Jean Valjean, my brother,
我用银餐具和这对烛台
I have bought your soul
赎回了你的灵魂
with that silverware and these candlesticks.
你是善的一员
You belong to good.
您看到我的40苏了吗  先生
Did you see my 40 sous, monsieur?
滚  快滚
Get lost! Go on!
你拿了我的钱  你是个臭贼
You've got my money. You're a dirty thief!
小瑞尔威
Petit Gervais!
妈妈  我累了
Maman, I'm tired.
二  三
Two, three...
好孩子
Oh, there's a good girl.
好了
All right.
妈妈爱你
Maman loves you.
非常爱你
Very much.
悲惨世界
第一季  第二集
*如果暴政妄图统治*
*Si le despotisme conspire*
*人民会奋起反抗*
*Conspirons la perte des rois*
*自由*
*Liberte*
*Liberte...*
-你的孩子们真可爱  夫人  -是啊
- You have two lovely children there, madame. - They are.
是啊  虽然我不该夸自己家孩子
They are, though I says so, I shouldn't.
爱潘妮和阿兹玛  我的心肝宝贝  是不是
Eponine and Azelma. My pride and joy, ain't you, girls?
你女儿也很可爱
But you've got a lovely little one too.
穿得这么好看
And such fine clothes.
你要不要坐下来  歇歇脚
Do you want to come and sit down, take the weight off your feet?
-谢谢  夫人  -让你女儿跟我女儿一起玩
- Thank you, madame. - Look, your little girl can play with mine.
-她叫什么  -珂赛特
- What's her name? - Cosette.
-你是远道而来吗  你好像很累  -从巴黎
- Have you come a long way? You look ever so tired. - From Paris.
我要去蒙特勒伊
I'm on my way to Montreuil.
听说那边有很不错的工作
I've heard there's some good work to be had there.
你丈夫呢
Where's hubby?
他...死了
He's... he's dead.
天啊
Oh, dear.
你肯定历尽了艰辛
So you've had a hard time of it, I dare say.
是啊
Yes, I have.
但我一旦有了稳定的工作  就能振作起来
But once I get into a steady job, I'll soon be on my feet again.
是啊  当然了
Yeah, of course you will.
但是  这个小不点跟着你
Still, it's not easy holding down a job
稳定的工作可不好找  对不对
with a little one in tow, is it?
是啊
No.
这家旅馆是你开的吗
Do you keep the inn here?
没错  亲爱的  德纳迪埃旅馆
Yeah, that's right, dear. Thenardier's the name.
看见那招牌了吗  那是我丈夫
See that sign there? That's my husband.
滑铁卢中士客栈
他是滑铁卢之战的英雄  救了一位上校的命
He was the hero of Waterloo. He saved a colonel's life.
背着他穿过枪林弹雨
Carried him on his back through a hail of bullets.
你丈夫是军人吗
Was your hubby a military man at all?
不是
No.
是诗人
A poet.
真好
Very nice.
虽然我觉得写诗赚不了多少钱
Not a lot of money in that though, I shouldn't wonder.
看看
Oh, look at that!
孩子们立马就变成朋友了  是不是
Children make friends in no time, don't they?
妈妈
Maman!
过路人肯定会以为她们是三姐妹
If you walked past that, you'd swear they were three sisters.
你能帮我照顾一阵孩子吗  夫人
Could you look after my child for a while, madame?
你说得对
You see, you were right.
带着小孩找工作  确实很难找到
It's hard to get work, especially when you have a child with you.
尤其是你孤身一人
Yeah, especially when you're on your own.
看到你的孩子们如此漂亮  被照管得这么好
When I saw your little ones looking so pretty and well cared for,
我就知道我来到这里是上帝的旨意
I knew that the good Lord had guided me here.
行吗
Will you?
我会付你钱的
I could pay.
六法郎一个月如何
Six francs a month.
七法郎
Seven.
-早上好  小姐  -先生
- Good morning, mademoiselle. - Monsieur.
必须七法郎才行啊
It'll have to be seven.
你不会想让我们克扣孩子的伙食费的吧
You wouldn't want us to skimp on her meals,
所以就给七法郎一个月  提前预支半年的
so that's seven francs, six months in advance.
我会在半年之内回来的  先生  我保证
I'll be back before then to get her, I'm sure, monsieur.
如果是那样的话我们会把钱退你
In that case we'd of course refund you,
但很抱歉  规矩就是规矩
but those are the terms, regrettably.
我们不能搞特例  不然我们怎么开得下去
We can't make any exceptions or where would we be?
七法郎六个月  一共是四十二法郎
Six sevens, that's 42 francs.
对
Yeah.
然后我们当然还需要考虑到初始花销
And we'll have to think about initial expenses too, of course.
我们象征性地收个十五法郎吧
Shall we say a nominal sum of 15 francs?
十五加四十二  一共五十七法郎
15 and 42, that's 57 francs.
五十七法郎
57?
我会付你的
I'll pay it.
你一定会像对亲生孩子一样好好照顾她的吧
You will look after her and love her like your own?
德纳迪埃  我们早就很喜欢她了不是吗
We love her already, don't we, Thenardier?
当然啦  我们怎么可能不喜欢她
Of course we do. How could we not?
来  我跟你说
Come here. Come on.
小姐  相信我
Believe me, mademoiselle,
你的小天使在我们的照顾下会感到很幸福的
your little darling will want for nothing in our loving care,
真的
yeah.
谢谢你们
Thank you.
过来过来  小天使  过来和老爹玩
Come here. Come here, little ones. Come and play with Daddy.
你泡的茶真不错
Oh, look! That's a lovely cup of tea you've got there, eh.
珂赛特  你要做一个大姑娘了
Cosette, now you're to be a good girl,
这对善良的夫妇
and this kind lady and gentleman
会照顾你一段时间
will look after you for a while.
-不要  -妈妈很快就回来接你了
- No. - And Maman will be back for you very soon.
不要  妈妈
No, Maman.
没事的  亲爱的
It's all right, my darling.
妈妈 妈妈
Maman! Maman!
妈妈  请别走
Maman, please!
妈妈
Maman.
-妈妈  -我会回来的  宝贝
- Maman. - I'll be back, darling.
妈妈  求求你别走
Maman, please!
-这都是为了大家好  你会懂的  -请别走
- It's all for the best, you'll see. - Please, no!
-不能总惯着她们  对吧  -妈妈
- Can't let them have all their own way, can we? - Maman!
-好了  跟妈妈说再见  -妈妈
- All right, bye, Maman. - Maman!
妈妈  请别走
Maman, please! Please!
过来玩
Come on.
妈妈
Maman.
马德林先生
Monsieur Madeleine.
马德林神父  如大家所知
Pere Madeleine, as he is known by many of you,
三年前来到了蒙特勒伊
came to Montreuil three years ago.
他刚到的那天
On the very day he arrived,
就冲进了一座房子
he rushed into a burning house
抱出了两个孩子  救了他们的性命
and brought out two children, saving their lives.
他为本地带来了新产业
He has brought new industry to the area
他的工厂成为了大家共同的财富源泉
and his factory has turned the fortunes of our town around.
我们都因他更加幸福
We are all better off because of Pere Madeleine.
他一直是一个智慧又慷慨的雇主
He has been a wise and generous employer.
从来不把自己的利益放在大家之前
Ever reluctant to put himself forward,
最后  他终于接受
he has at last been persuaded
知恩图报的市民们劝说
by the grateful citizens
接受了蒙特勒伊的市长一职
to accept the office of Mayor of Montreuil.
女士们先生们  马德林先生
Mesdames et Messieurs, Monsieur Madeleine.
马德林先生
Monsieur Madeleine!
蒙特勒伊的市民们  朋友们
Citizens of Montreuil, my friends...
感谢大家
..I thank you for the, erm, trust that you've, you've...
对我的信任
you've shown in me.
祝大家日安
Good day.
马德林先生
Monsieur Madeleine!
打扰了  我正在找些活干
Excuse me. I'm looking for some work.
来吧
Come.
来吧  没什么好怕的
Come. Nothing to be frightened of.
坐下吧
Sit here.
你的姓名
Your name?
芳汀  先生
Fantine, monsieur,
芳汀·蒂博
Fantine Thibault.
你刚到这里来的吗
And you are new in the town?
是的
Yes.
-我过去在巴黎生活  -你在那里做什么
- I was living in Paris. - What work were you doing there?
我在一家裁缝店里缝衣服
I was a seamstress at a dressmaker's.
这边的工作也需要灵活的手指
Well, the work here needs nimble fingers too,
-你觉得你能学会吗  -可以
- so, you think you can learn it? - Yes.
如果您要我的话  我一定拼命干活
And if you take me, I'll work very hard.
您不会后悔的
You won't regret it.
好
Good.
你的家庭情况是怎么样的
So what are your, erm, family circumstances?
我孤身一人  先生
I am alone in the world, sir.
-没有丈夫吗  -没有
- No husband? - No.
没有情人
No lover?
没有孩子
No children?
像我说过的  先生
As I said, sir, I'm...
我孤身一人
I'm alone in the world.
芳汀  对于你和我来说
It's very important to me and to you, Fantine,
你绝对的诚实是非常重要的
that you're completely honest with me.
您不相信我
You don't believe me?
再说您为什么要关心我的生活呢
Why should you care about my life anyway?
我所有的工人我都关心
I care about all my workers.
那么
So...
你是孤身一人了
..All alone in the world?
是的  先生
Yes, monsieur.
我先给你一个月的试用期
I'll take you on a month's probation.
如果你干得好  你会赚到钱的
And if you work well, you can prosper here.
谢谢您  先生  谢谢
Thank you, monsieur. Thank you.
维克蒂尼安太太  请带她去她的桌子
Madame Victurnien, will you show her to a table?
你可以马上开始工作吗
Are you are able to begin right away?
-当然了  马德林先生  -很好
- Yes, of course, Monsieur Madeleine. - Good.
-那就去吧  -再次感谢您  先生
- Well, go now. - Thank you again, monsieur.
谢谢
Thank you.
他的床头想来都是足金的
His bedhead's supposed to be solid gold.
雕刻着天使啊翅膀啊  等等的
Carved angels, wings - everything.
我可不介意在他的床上展开我的双翼
I wouldn't mind spreading my wings in his bed.
怎么了
What?!
芳汀  你得轻点  别把它弄断了
Be a bit gentler, Fantine. You don't want to snag it.
这样很对  芳汀
That's good, Fantine.
你开始掌握了
You're getting the hang of it.
市长先生
Monsieur le Maire!
好了  孩子们
All right, boys?
给你们
There you are.
还好吗
All right?
来  拿着  乖孩子
Here, take that. Good boy.
代笔人
德纳迪埃先生和太太  别来无恙...
And I hope this finds you well, Monsieur and Madame Thenardier...
珂赛特也一直都挺乖的吧
..And that my Cosette has been a good girl for you.
告诉她妈妈爱她
Tell her Maman loves her
给她送上一千个吻
and sends her a thousand kisses,
希望很快就可以去领她
and hopes to be able to fetch her very soon.
接她  应该说接她
Collect her. Collect her.
谢谢
Thank you.
她给你送上一千个吻
And she sends you a thousand kisses. Mwah!
她希望很快就可以来接她
And hopes to be able to collect her very soon.
"您永远谦卑的..."  好家伙
"I remain your very humble..." Oooh!
等等等等
Et cetera, et cetera.
词用得真花哨  她寄钱来了吗
Very fancy language! She sent the money, eh?
寄上额外一点钱来给亲爱的小家伙买点好吃的
Sent a bit extra to buy the dear little thing some treats.
这可不行
That won't be happening.
如果她有钱能额外寄过来
If she's got enough to send a bit extra,
那我们就该涨价了  该涨多少  十二法郎
it's time to raise the rates. What do you reckon? 12 francs?
不  十五  我今天就写信给她
No, 15. I'll write to her today.
我倒是可以来点好吃的  德纳迪埃
I could do with a treat, Thenardier.
到时候就给你来点  我的小亲亲
And you shall get one, my little pigeon.
到时候吧  等情况好些
All in good time, when things look up a bit.
所有的余款都要拿去付账
Any spare cash has got to go towards the bills.
我不明白是怎么回事  可无论我做什么
I don't know what it is, but whatever I do,
好像都赚不了钱
nothing seems to prosper.
路那头的野鸭旅店有好多客人
The Wild Duck down the road gets plenty of custom.
我这怎么就不行呢
Why not me?
回你的角落去  加夫罗什
Back in your corner, Gavroche!
快点  你这个小崽子  离我远点
Come on, you little beast, and out of my sight.
知道吗  德纳迪埃  真是怪了
Do you know, it's a strange thing, Thenardier,
我一直没办法喜欢上她
but I've never been able to take to that one.
我可以为女儿们做任何事  但那肮脏的小东西
I could do anything for my girls, but that nasty little creature
根本激发不起我心中的母性
doesn't bring any maternal instincts out in me at all.
命盘不好  亲爱的  你做什么都没用
Born under a bad sign, love. Nothing you can do about it.
知道吗  德纳迪埃  你总说
Do you know, Thenardier, you know you said how
-这里总是很冷清  太怪了  -对  亲爱的
- it's funny this place never seems to prosper? - Yes, my dear.
你有没有考虑过  亲爱的
Have you ever considered, my love,
人言可畏
that people talk?
比如马车夫可能会说
And the coachman, like, he might say,
别去那家店  先生  德纳迪埃给啤酒掺水
"Oh, don't go in there, sir, cos Thenardier waters down the beer
还附赠缺斤少两
"And short changes you into the bargain!"
我常觉得你应该在门外放个标牌  写着
I've often thought you could have a sign outside saying,
"想被骗就进来"
"Come in here if you want to be swindled."
你把嘴闭上
You shut your mouth.
如果想要你的建议  我会问的  懂了吗
When I want your advice, I'll ask for it, yeah?
滚
Go!
看什么看  你也想挨打吗
What are you looking at? You want some too?
市长先生
Monsieur le Maire,
新警察局长来见你了
the new Chief of Police is here to see you.
市长先生  我觉得我们应该认识一下
Monsieur le Maire, I thought we should become acquainted.
我叫沙威
My name is Javert.
于昨晚抵达蒙特勒伊
I arrived in Montreuil last night.
请坐  督察
Please take a seat, Inspector.
-你想喝一杯吗  -不了  谢谢  市长先生
- Can I offer you a drink? - No, thank you, Monsieur le Maire.
原谅我  这是您偏好的称呼吗
Forgive me, is that how you prefer to be addressed?
我听过别人称呼您为马德林神父
I have heard you called Pere Madeleine?
不  市长先生就可以
No, Monsieur le Maire will do.
您的这个工厂非常好
You have a fine establishment here.
谢谢
Thank you.
我听说您通过雇佣所有想工作的人
I am told you have restored the prosperity of the town
重振了这个城镇的繁荣
by giving employment to all those who are willing to work.
因此  这里的犯罪很少
Consequently, there's very little crime here.
是的  我愿意这样相信
Yes, I like to think that that is so.
但是贼偷东西不是因为他又穷又绝望
But a thief does not steal because he is poor and desperate,
他偷东西因为他有犯罪心理
he steals because he has a criminal mentality,
因为他是堕落的人
because he is degenerate,
简单地说  因为他是
because he is, to put it simply...
邪恶的人
..wicked.
我必须得说我们意见相左
Well, there I have to tell you that we disagree.
是吗
Really?
我相信我们中的大多数人可善可恶
I believe most of us are capable of good and evil,
我们成为什么样子取决于境遇
and how we turn out depends on our circumstances
和我们受到的对待
and how we are treated.
这个结论是您根据自身经验得出的吗
And has your own experience led you to that conclusion?
是的
Yes, it has.
市长先生
Monsieur le Maire,
我期待今后就此话题更多地探讨
I look forward to many interesting discussions on this topic.
不过现在  我作为警察局长向您保证
For now, let me assure you that as your Chief of Police,
我将尽我所能地
I shall do everything in my power
找出  逮捕并惩罚
to seek out, apprehend and punish
您的城镇中的每一个犯罪者
every single wrong-doer in your fine town.
很高兴听到这个  警督
Glad to hear it, Inspector.
我认为你在蒙特勒伊的任务不会太艰巨
I think your task won't be too demanding here in Montreuil.
也许如此
Perhaps.
粗略检查之下
On cursory inspection,
您的市民看起来满足并守序
your citizens seem to be contented and well ordered.
你这样野心勃勃的人为什么要选择这样的职位
So, why does an ambitious man choose a posting like this?
您推断我有野心
You deduce that I am ambitious.
离开监狱系统后  我全身心投入
Since I left the Prison Service, I have dedicated myself
不仅追捕明显的罪犯
to pursuing not only the obvious offences,
还有那些藏起来的
but the hidden ones.
不仅是当下的罪犯  还有以前的
Not only in the present, but in the past.
有时候一个人可能看起来成功富有
Sometimes a man may be seen to be rich, successful,
品行端正
prosperous, virtuous...
然而同时他可能隐藏着一个秘密
..While all the time he may be harbouring a secret.
以前的丑恶行径
Something rotten in his past.
应该让这种秘密隐藏下去吗
Is it right that such a secret should remain hidden?
应该让这种人继续享受
Is it right that such a man should continue to enjoy the fruits
他不为人知的罪恶的成果吗
of his wickedness undiscovered?
你认为这个城镇里有这种人
You think there is such a man here in this town?
这种人到处都是  市长先生
There are such men everywhere, Monsieur le Maire.
所以我的工作才如此迷人
That's what makes my work so fascinating.
当然了  必须得有无可争议的证据证明他有罪
Of course, one must have incontrovertible proof of guilt.
这需要时间
And that takes time.
我不想占用你宝贵的时间
Well, I don't want to keep you.
-认识你是我的荣幸  -我也是
- It's been a pleasure to make your acquaintance. - Likewise.
我一直在想  跟你交谈时
You know, I've been thinking, as we've talked,
你让我想起了一个我曾经熟识的一个人
you remind me of someone I used to know rather well at one time.
他偷了一个孩子的东西
He stole from a child
从未为自己的罪行付出过代价
and never paid for his crime.
我现在想不起他的名字了
I can't recall his name now.
晚安吧
Ah, well. Goodnight...
市长先生
..Monsieur le Maire.
我还是不敢相信他没邀请我
I still can't believe he didn't invite me.
-范范会邀请你的  不是吗  范比  -闭嘴
- Fabs would, wouldn't you, Fabby? - Shut up!
有人去过那吗
Has anyone ever been up there?
-我打赌他会让芳汀进  -为什么会让我进去
- I bet he'd let Fantine in though. - Why me?
因为他喜欢你  我们都看见他看你了
Cos he likes you and we've seen him looking.
-我猜他会让你进他房间  -让你上他的床
- I bet he'd let you in his room. - Let you in his bed!
-如果他要求做  你会就范吗  -不会
- Would you, if he asked? - No!
好吧  别装了
All right, hoity-toity.
-那是什么  芳汀  挺漂亮的  -没什么
- What's that, Fantine? That's pretty. - It's nothing.
瞧  范范  是只小鸟
Look, Fabs, it's a little bird!
真好看
Ah, that is nice.
-给谁做的  -没谁
- Who's it for? - No-one.
当心  薇琪过来了
Look out, Vicky's coming.
这是什么
What's this?
给我看看
Show me.
谁要你做这个了
Who told you to do this?
没谁  夫人  但我的任务已经完成了
No-one, madame, but I'd finished my quota.
任务做完了也不能在这自娱自乐
You're not here to amuse yourself when you finish your quota.
-应该接新任务来做  -抱歉  夫人
- You ask for more work. - Sorry, madame.
-我真想当场解雇你  -请不要解雇我  夫人
- I've a good mind to dismiss you on the spot. - Please, no, madame.
求你了
Please.
这是最后警告
Consider this a final warning.
讨厌的老贱人
Nasty old bitch.
"我知道你和我们一样
"I know your little girl's health and happiness
关心你女儿是否健康快乐
"is as dear to you as it is to my dear wife and me.
只需一小笔"  一小笔
"A trifling sum..." A trifling sum?
这个家伙写得真可恨
This fellow writes abominably.
"只需一小笔钱  每月15法郎"
"A trifling sum of 15 francs a month."
每月15法郎
15 francs a month?!
我没这么多钱
I can't pay that!
你还想不想听后面的了
Do you want to hear the rest or not?
"我们希望尽快收到这笔钱"
"We expect to receive this money due to us very promptly."
代笔人
你说她是个妓女
She was some kind of a prostitute, you say?
我不喜欢说别人坏话  但是真的
Well, I don't like to speak ill of anyone, but, yes,
但这小女孩肯定是罪恶的果实
and no doubt the little girl was conceived in sin
成了她的累赘
and had become some sort of encumbrance.
不用想就知道  对吗
Doesn't bear thinking about, does it?
这些人过的都是不正常的生活
These people don't lead natural lives.
她可能现在都把自己女儿忘干净了
She's probably forgotten all about the little girl now.
她还在写信给你
She still writes to you.
是的  时不时吧  她想起来就写
Oh, yeah, I mean, now and then, when she thinks about it.
"希望你好好照顾她"  之类的
"I hope you're looking after her proper", and all that, and so on.
但对我们还有这个小姑娘有什么用呢
but what good is that to us or the little girl?
我觉得
I think...
你们被利用了
..You have been taken advantage of.
你说得对  夫人
You're right there, madame.
你想留宿一两晚吗
Are you thinking of staying a night or two?
前面有间不错的房间  现在没有人住
We have a lovely room on the front that's vacant just now.
我已经在野鸭旅店住下了  马夫推荐的
I've taken a room at the Wild Duck. The coachman recommended it.
我是滑铁卢战役中的英雄
I was one of the heroes of Waterloo!
拿破仑亲自授予了我荣誉军团勋章
I was awarded the Legion d'Honneur by Napoleon himself.
-你想看看吗  -不用了  谢谢
- Would you care to examine it? - No, thank you.
-不了吗  好吧  -祝安  谢谢你的时间
- No... yeah. - Good day to you. Thank you for your time.
可悲的老女人
Miserable old cow, eh?
算我倒霉
Tant pis!
闭嘴
Oh, shut up!
拿破仑万岁
Vive Napoleon!
拿破仑·波拿巴对法国的伤害
Napoleon Bonaparte did more harm to France
比英国  俄国和奥地利的军队加起来还要大
than all the armies of Britain, Russia and Austria combined.
听听  就是一个野蛮人  一个粗人
Hear, hear. A barbarian, a savage,
感谢上帝  现在他是个遭人鄙视的流犯
and thanks be to God, now a despised exile.
然而这位年轻人
But here is a young man
有着正确的想法
who thinks in the right way.
先生们
Gentlemen,
这是我的孙子
my grandson...
马吕斯·彭眉胥
..Marius Pontmercy.
拿破仑就是一个卖国贼
Napoleon was a traitor to his country
我父亲也是一个卖国贼
and my father was a traitor to his country too.
我唾弃他们
I spit upon them both!
国王万岁  法国万岁
Vive le Roi! Vive la France!
好孩子
Good boy.
先生  这封信刚刚寄到了
Monsieur, this letter has just arrived.
年轻人
Well, young man,
看来你父亲
it seems your father
已经离死不远了
is on his deathbed.
对此你怎么看
Now, what do you say... to that?
-很好  -哈哈
- Good! - Ha-ha!
我也觉得
And so do I!
So do I!
你可以离开了  亲爱的
Well, off you go, my dear.
先生  这男孩应该去见父亲最后一面
The boy should see his father before he dies, monsieur.
这是理所应当的
It's only right.
如果他想去  我不会阻止他的
Well, I won't forbid it, if he wants to go.
你想去吗
Do you?
要是你不去  你会后悔一辈子的
If you don't, you might be sorry your whole life.
没关系  我陪你去
It's all right, I'll go with you.
女人
Women!
不得不爱  不是吗
You have to love them, don't you?
你就是个骗子  对吗
You're a liar, aren't you?
市长先生  快来
Monsieur le Maire, come quickly!
-马德林先生  -夫人
- Monsieur Madeleine! - Madame...
-先生  别  -我必须得去
- Monsieur... No, please! - No, I have to go.
先生  先生
Monsieur! Monsieur!
救救我
Help me!
把这车卸了
Unload that cart!
把马牵好
Control that horse!
来人把马给松开
Someone untether the horse.
救救我
Help me!
坚持住  康斯特布尔  我们会救你出来
Hold on, Constable, we'll get you out!
去找人帮忙
Get someone to get it!
过来得20分钟  等人来他都被压死了
That's 20 minutes from here. He'll be crushed to death by then!
所有人都在这了  市长先生
It's all in hand, Monsieur le Maire.
救救我
Help me!
恭喜你  市长先生
Congratulations, Monsieur le Maire.
太有影响力了
Most instructive.
又有多人见证
And witnessed by so many.
马德林先生
Monsieur Madeleine.
现在不行
Not now.
这个伤风败俗女子
This immoral young woman
就是这家工厂  这个小镇的耻辱
is a disgrace to the factory and the town.
那不是真的  我是无辜的
It's not true. I'm innocent!
很抱歉  先生  她比妓女好不到哪去
I regret to say, monsieur, she is no better than a whore.
她有个私生子  还把孩子丢在蒙费梅伊
She has a bastard child, she abandoned at Montfermeil.
我从没抛弃她
....I never abandoned her!
我没抛弃她  我每月都寄十五法郎
I never abandoned her. I send 15 francs per month.
比我一半的工资还多了
More than half my wages.
骗人的小婊子  你真丢人
Lying little whore. You're a disgrace!
市长先生  相信我  珂赛特是我的一切
Monsieur le Maire, believe me. My Cosette is all I care about.
骗人的小婊子
Lying little whore!
她上班是就在做这个事
This is what she does when she's supposed to be working.
-给她小杂种的玩具  -相信我
- A toy for her little bastard. - Believe me...
够了  你们两个  够了
Enough, both of you! Enough!
芳汀·蒂博
Fantine Thibault?
是的  先生
Yes, monsieur.
我记得我问过你的家庭情况
I remember I asked you about your family
你说你在世上孤身一人
and you said you were alone in the world.
我想要是我跟你说了我的孩子
I thought if I told you about my little girl
你就会解雇我
you'd turn me away.
你骗了我
You lied to me!
这又没什么坏处
There was no harm in it.
-我那时怕你  -别听她的  先生
- I was frightened of you. - Don't listen to her, monsieur.
-她就是个淫妇  -我不是  我不是
- She's an immoral woman. - I am not! I am not.
但孩子是你的
But the child is yours?
-这有罪吗  -她抛弃了她的孩子
- Is that a crime? - And she abandoned it.
不  我没有
No, I didn't!
-请相信我  -我无法相信你
- Please believe me. - I can't believe you!
你被开除了
You're dismissed.
但我还能去干什么呢
But what am I going to do?
这里有50法郎  我建议你离开这里  小姐
There's 50 francs. I advise you to leave the town, mademoiselle.
但我不能走  我还欠别人钱
But I can't leave this town. I owe people money here.
那就去找别的工作
Well, find some other employment!
他们都说你是位善良的好心人
They said that you were a kind and good man.
我也以为你是
And I thought you were.
但其实不然
But you're not.
你是个恶魔
You're a monster!
-恶魔  -够了  够了
- A monster! - That's enough! That's enough!
你怎敢侮辱我们好心的马德林神父
How dare you insult our good Pere Madeleine?
滚出去
Out now!
现在就走
This minute!
驾
Come on!
驾  驾  别慌
Come on! Come on! Steady!
巴黎警察局总部
总督察  我叫沙威
Chief Inspector, my name is Javert.
我刚接管蒙特勒伊地区
I have just taken charge in Montreuil.
沙威探长  你来巴黎干什么
Inspector Javert, what are you doing in Paris?
我发现了一名危险的罪犯
I've identified a dangerous criminal.
-我前来与您商议如何处置此人  -他是谁
- I've come to consult you on how to proceed. - Who is this man?
他的名字叫冉·阿让
His name is Jean Valjean.
多年前我在土伦监狱认识了他
I knew him years ago at the prison hulks at Toulon.
他出狱后不久就偷窃孩童财物并逃跑
He stole from a child within days of his release and fled.
是个力大又残忍的人
A man of exceptional strength and brutality.
如今他在外假扮成蒙特勒伊市长
He's now posing as the Mayor of Montreuil.
你错了
You're mistaken.
总督察  我认识此人
I tell you, I know the man.
冉·阿让已被拘留
Jean Valjean is in custody.
四天前他在阿伊勒欧克洛谢被捕
He was arrested four days ago in Ailly-le-Haut-Clocher.
到时将会接受审判
In due course, he will stand trial.
这个男人承认自己是冉·阿让了吗
Has this man confessed to being Jean Valjean?
还没有  但他会的
Not yet, but he will.
-已经有人指认他了  -但是先生
- He has been identified. - But monsieur...
记住  对公众人物
And bear in mind, it's a very serious matter,
提出指控是非常严重的一件事
making accusations against important public figures.
我建议你多加小心  沙威探长
I'd advise you to be more careful, Inspector Javert.
晚安  市长先生
Evening, Monsieur le Maire.
父亲
Mon pere?
你来了
You came.
好孩子
Good boy.
现在你是彭眉胥男爵了
You will be Baron Pontmercy now.
拿破仑亲自在滑铁卢
The honour was bestowed on me
授予我这项荣誉
by Napoleon himself at Waterloo.
如今由你继承
Now it is yours by right.
有一个人
There's a man...
名叫德纳迪埃
..Called Thenardier.
他救了我的命
He saved my life.
如果你今后遇见他  尽你所能款待他
If you ever meet him, do the best, you can.
芳汀
蒙特勒伊克拉佩小街
孩子感染了粟疹热病
The child has caught a miliary fever.
我的天
Oh, my God.
他们需要钱买药  40法郎
They're asking for money for medicine. 40 francs.
我可怜的孩子
My poor child.
为什么不把你女儿接到这来
Why not go and fetch your daughter here?
让她和我一起过这悲惨的生活吗
And have her share my wretched life?
我不想令她蒙羞
I don't want to bring shame on her head.
她现在这样就好
She's better off where she is.
但天晓得我要去哪赚钱供她留在那里了
Though God knows how I'll find the money for her keep now.
你是个非常美丽的女人
..You're a very pretty young woman.
而漂亮女人
There's always ways...
总有办法
that a pretty young woman can...
找到生计
..Make a living.
如果你明白我的意思
If you know what I mean.
祝您晚安  先生
Bonsoir, monsieur.
我又买又卖  今夜我又买又卖
I'm buying and I'm selling, I'm selling and I'm buying tonight.
如果你没有头发和牙齿  你能改变自己的生命
If you're bald and toothless, you can change your life.
今夜我又买又卖  女士们先生们
I'm selling and I'm buying tonight, ladies and gentlemen!
我有闪闪金发  也有乌亮黑发
I've got golden, I've got glossy black,
有卷发  有直发
I've got curly, I've got straight,
有长发  有短发
I've got long and I've got short.
来  摸摸这个
Here, have a feel of this one.
是不是如丝绸般柔软
Is that soft as silk?
还有牙齿
And teeth!
你们不想今晚带着一口亮丽的新牙回家吗
How'd you like to go home tonight with a lovely new set of teeth?
你们手头的东西可以在我这抵一些价钱
And I'll take what you've got in part exchange.
没有比这更公平的了  不是吗
Can't say fairer than that now, can I?
来了一位美人
Oh, I say, there's a beauty.
请让路  女士们  让她过来
Make way, ladies. Let her come through.
过来  亲爱的
That's it, my dear.
我好久都没见过一头这么美的秀发了
Now, that is as lovely a head of hair as I've seen in a long while.
全放下来看看  亲爱的
Let it all down, my dear.
-你要卖吗  -多少钱
- Are you selling, dear? - How much?
-十法郎  -只有这么点
- Ten francs. - Is that all?
这是最高价了  随你在哪也卖不了更多
That's the top rate. You won't get more anywhere.
但如果你能考虑舍弃
But if you was thinking of parting
这些亮丽的白牙
with those lovely white teeth, now.
只要前面两颗
Just the two front ones even.
我就能给你两个拿破仑金币
I could give you two Napoleons for those.
值40法郎
40 francs.
所有牙一起50
50 altogether.
只要五分钟就好
Just five minutes' work.
你意下如何
What do you say?
好吧
All right.
稍事休息  女士们先生们
A short intermission, ladies and gentlemen.
别走开
Don't go away!
请在那坐下  亲爱的
Sit yourself down there, my love.
你叫什么名字
What's your name?
芳汀
Fantine.
真好听
Lovely.
瞧瞧这个  母亲
Look at this, mother.
这么好的货色  我们可不经常遇见
We don't often see anything as good as this, do we?
你确定你想好了要做这个吗
Now, you quite sure you want to go through with this?
你还可以改变心意
You're allowed to change your mind, you know.
我想好了
I'm sure.
那就开始吧
Here we go, then.
好了  快剪完了
That's it. Nearly done.
棒极了  母亲
Goody good, mother.
好了  我相信它很快又会长回来的
There. It'll soon grow again, I dare say.
帮我把她按住  母亲
Right, help me hold her still, mother.
快下来了
It's coming.
第一枚
Number one.
快下来了
Shh, it's coming.
这才像话
That's more like it.
她肯定很有钱
She must be rolling in it!
我觉得我们要的还不够多  你说呢
I don't think we've been asking for enough, what do you think?
可怜的小女孩正生命垂危
The poor little girl's at death's door
亟待医生的救治  你觉得该要多少钱
and the doctor's demanding, what do you reckon?
-100法郎  -好极了
- 100? - Yes!
继续  好好擦
Go on, do it properly.
"我们恳求你能为小珂赛特竭尽所能
"We beg that you do all you can for little Cosette.
德纳迪埃"
Thenardier."
告诉他们我会尽快寄钱过去
Tell them I'll send it as soon as I can.
你打算怎么筹钱呢
And how are you going to raise the money, hm?
我卖掉了头发和牙齿
I've sold my hair and my teeth.
我应该会继续把剩下的也卖掉
I might as well get on with it and sell the rest.
小姐
Ah, mademoiselle...
-真可惜  -你也这么觉得吗
- What a shame. - You think so?
你搞错了方向  亲爱的
You've gone about it the wrong way round, my dear.
你应该在卖掉
You should have gone on the game
一头秀发和亮丽白牙之前就加入行当
before you sold your pretty hair and your lovely white teeth.
你现在这个样子  谁还会要你
Who's going to take you, looking like that?
滚开
Get out!
芳汀  是你吗
Fantine? Is that you?
芳汀
Fantine?
-芳汀  -别管她
- Fantine. - Leave her.
晚安  女士们
Evening, ladies!
-多么美好的夜晚  -的确如此
- Lovely night for it. - Indeed it is.
天哪
Oh, my God!
这是谁啊
What have we got here?
好惊悚啊
What a sight!
你收费多少  秃子
And how much do you charge, baldy?
你觉得值多少钱就收多少  先生
Whatever you think it's worth, monsieur.
那我觉得一文不值呢
How about nothing, then?
你们听到了吗  先生们  一文不值怎么样
You hear that, gentlemen? How about nothing?
她就是一文不值
That's all she's worth!
但我得生活  先生  就像你一样
But I have to live, monsieur, the same as you.
跟我一样吗  你这厚颜无耻的女人
The same as me? You cheeky cow!
你们听说过这样的事吗
Did you ever hear the like of it?!
你觉得我这么做是为了找乐子吗
You think I do this for fun?
我是为了养活我的女儿
I do it to feed my little girl.
所以你要是不想跟我做生意
So, if you don't want business,
就请行行好...
do me a favour...
走吧
and move along.
我甘受责备
I stand rebuked.
请原谅  小姐
I humbly beg your pardon, mademoiselle.
请问你叫什么名字  小姐
Might I ask your name, mademoiselle?
我叫芳汀  先生
Fantine, monsieur.
晚安  芳汀
Bonsoir, Fantine.
希望你能原谅我
I-I hope I am forgiven.
晚安  先生
Bonsoir, monsieur.
芳汀  送你个东西
Fantine, something for you.
救命
Help!
你跟我来
You, come with me.
这是一种不能容忍的暴行
This is an outrage that cannot be tolerated.
一个受人尊敬的拥有财产的公民
A respectable property-owning citizen
被一个妓女袭击
attacked by a common prostitute!
-把这个娼妓关进牢房  -遵命
- Take this whore to the cells. - Yes, sir.
你被判刑六个月
You've got six months.
六个月吗  我的孩子怎么办
Six months? But what about my child?
这不关我的事  把她带走
That's no concern of mine. Take her away.
求你了  沙威先生  我不是这样的人
Please, Monsieur Javert! I wasn't always like this!
我本是个好女孩...
I was a good girl...
把她带走  她身上散发着堕落的恶臭
Take her away! She stinks of degradation.
请等一下
One moment!
市长先生
Monsieur le Maire.
Monsieur le Maire?
抓住她  你们这些笨蛋
Seize her, you fool!
你们看到这个男人了吗
You see this man here?
看到这个被你们称为市长先生的魔鬼了吗
You see this monster here that you call Monsieur le Maire?
一切都是他的错
It's all his fault!
他应该是个好人  看看他都干了什么
He's supposed to be so good. What did he do?
他把我扔到街上
He threw me out on the street.
你们知道为什么吗  因为我想照顾我的女儿
And you know why? Because I tried to care for my little girl!
魔鬼市长
Monster of a mayor!
市长先生是魔鬼吗
Monsieur le Maire, a monster?
你现在明白了  可以放我走吗
You understand now. You'll let me go now?
我会做个安分的妓女
I'll be a good little whore now.
他们可以对我为所欲为  我不会抱怨
They can do what they like with me and I won't complain.
我只想工作养活我的孩子
All I want is to be able to work to feed my child
把她从蒙费梅伊接回来
and fetch her from Montfermeil.
求你了  我...我不能呼吸
Please, I can't... I can't breathe.
-请感受一下  -滚开
- Feel it. - Get away from me!
不  我来照顾她
No! I will take her into my care.
你无权这么做
You have no right!
芳汀  我不该赶你走
Fantine, I was wrong to dismiss you.
我错了
I was wrong.
也许为时已晚  但请让我弥补一下
Perhaps it's too late, but let me try to make amends.
我会帮你还债  找到你的孩子
I'll, I'll pay your debts, I'll find your child
让你们在一起
so that you can be together.
你不用再工作了
You need never work again.
我会照顾你  我保证
I'll take care of you, I promise.
真的吗
You mean it?
你不是在开玩笑吗
It's not a joke?
我现在带你去医院  来
Now let me take you to the infirmary. Come on.
-跟我走  -不  我不同意
- Come with me. - No, I forbid it.
这个女人被判刑了  她得去坐牢
This woman has been sentenced then she is going to prison.
-把她带去牢房  -别碰她
- Take her to the cells. - Don't touch her!
沙威先生  在市政事务上  我的级别高于你
Monsieur Javert, in municipal matters, I outrank you.
我警告你  别在此事上跟我过不去
I warn you, don't cross me over this.
这个女人对你来说到底意味着什么  市长先生
What exactly does this woman mean to you, Monsieur le Maire?
她是需要我帮助的人
Someone who needs my help.
一个娼妓吗
A common whore?
她是低人一等的人
She is the lowest of the low.
你要冒着名誉风险去帮助这样一个人吗
You would risk your good name to help a creature like that?
她也是是上帝的造物  沙威先生
She's one of God's creatures, Monsieur Javert,
而且她虽然毫无过错却经受了如此大的痛苦
and she has suffered grievously through no fault of her own.
是我伤害了她  所以现在我要设法补救
I injured her myself, and now I want to make amends if I can.
你让我无话可说
You astonish me.
请你不要挡着我的路
Now stand out of my way.
你在这儿干吗
What are you doing here?
我在
I'm...
我在为你祈祷
I'm praying for you.
也为我自己
And for myself.
能不能请你
Will you...
叫人把我的女儿
..send for my daughter...
珂赛特找来
Cosette, please?
当然可以了
Yes, of course.
需要的话我可以亲自去找她
If necessary, I'll go for her myself.
我  我曾是个罪人
I've been a...a sinner.
但如果珂赛特在我身边的话
But when I have Cosette with me...
那就意味着
..it will mean...
上帝已经原谅我了
that God has forgiven me.
市长先生  沙威督察来了
Inspector Javert is here, Monsieur le Maire.
请坐吧  督察
Sit down, Inspector.
谢谢您的好意  市长先生  我更想站着
Thank you, Monsieur le Maire. I prefer to stand.
请便  你来意是为何啊
As you wish. What can I do for you?
我是来检举一位警官所犯下的
I have come to report a serious misdemeanour
十分严重的罪行的
by an officer of the police.
哪一位警官呢
Which officer?
我自己
Myself.
我是前来辞任的
I have come to offer my resignation.
为什么呢
For what reason?
首先  我想为我早些时候的行为道歉
Firstly, I'd like to apologise for my conduct earlier and...
我在巴黎警察总署当众侮辱了您
I denounced you to police headquarters in Paris.
我还错误的怀疑您
I suspected you, wrongly as it turns out,
是个臭名昭著的重罪犯
to be a notorious felon,
是我曾经的24601号囚犯
once known to me as Prisoner Number 24601.
是个叫冉·阿让的人
A man named Jean Valjean.
但是你错了
But you were wrong.
嗯
Yes.
看样子是的
It seems I was.
你
What, erm...
你为什么改变主意了呢
What made you change your mind?
市长先生  真正的阿让
Monsieur le Maire, the real Valjean...
被抓到了
has been found.
什么
What?
他将因多项指控在阿拉斯的法庭接受审判
He's about to stand trial in Arras for a number of offences,
其中包括从一个叫小瑞尔威的孩子那里
including the theft of a coin from a child
窃取硬币
who went by the name of Petit Gervais.
小瑞尔威
Petit Gervais?
Petit Gervais.
您对这个名字耳熟吗  市长先生
Does the name mean anything to you, Monsieur le Maire?
这个人认罪了吗
Has this man confessed?
还没有
No.
但是他的谎言一定会在法庭上被揭穿
No, but no doubt his lies will be exposed in court
而他将会被判处
and he'll be sentenced to penal servitude...
服终身苦役
for life.
他已经完了
It's over for him.
审判就在明天
The trial is tomorrow.
我今晚会乘马车去阿拉斯
I'll take the coach to Arras tonight
那将会是我作为巡官所履行的最后职责
and that will be my last duty as Police Inspector.
晚安  市长先生
Goodnight, Monsieur le Maire.
有什么事吗  嬷嬷
What can I do for you, Sister?
我们的病人  芳汀·蒂博  那个娼妓
Our patient, Fantine Thibault, the prostitute.
别这么叫她
Don't call her that.
医生让我告诉您  她现在很虚弱
The doctor wanted you to know that she... She's very weak.
她应该时日无多了
She has very little time left on this Earth
而且她一直在念叨希望见到她的孩子
and she speaks constantly of seeing her child.
好的好的  我知道
Yes, yes, I know that.
医生说如果她想在死前见到她的孩子的话
The doctor says if she is to see her child
那个孩子得立刻...
before she dies, the child should be...
好的  我知道了  嬷嬷
Yes, I understand, Sister!
请原谅我的失礼
I beg your pardon.
谢谢你  嬷嬷
Thank you, Sister.
请尽你所能去帮她
Please do your best for her.
我还有其他要做的事  失陪了
Now there are things that I have to attend to. Excuse me.
你拿了  对不对  你拿了我的钱
You've got it, haven't you? You've got my money!
你是个臭贼
You're a dirty thief!
诅咒你
A curse on you!
维克蒂尼安太太  马德林先生
Madame Victurnien. Monsieur Madeleine!
我有件事麻烦你  如果你愿意帮忙的话
I have an errand for you, if you'd be so kind.
-你记得芳汀·蒂博吗  -我记得
- You remember Fantine Thibault? - Indeed I do.
她住院了  她现在病得很重
She's in hospital, she's very ill.
我需要你去蒙费梅伊找到她的小女儿
I need you to go to Montfermeil and fetch her little girl.
把她带过来
Bring her here.
本来我想自己去的  但我还要去其他地方
I'd go myself, but I... There's somewhere else I have to be.